hi I'm Brett contas and in this video
I'm going to go over a very important
concept and this concept is on
neuromuscular training neuromuscular
re-education motor control training
whatever you want to call it has
different names but this is something
that comes up in the literature you know
maybe five studies every month will will
pop up and you get a really good grip on
this this um this topic once you're
reading this stuff every month month in
month out and this is something as a as
a beginner strength coach I didn't know
much about and I was wrong with my
assumptions and I think a lot of you
guys are probably in the same boat you
probably have this topic pegged wrong
and it's really really important that
you understand this so um basically the
the topic is about you know how do we
improve people's form not with I'm not
just talking about lifting weights I'm
talking about um you know Athletics
sporting skills say jumping Landing
sprinting agility cutting side to side
change of Direction throwing um swinging
all these different activities let's
take jumping for example let's say you
film somebody jumping and you notice
they come down and their knees cave in
you know valgus collapse knee valgus and
they jump up or when they land they come
down and land and their knees cave in or
maybe when they're squatting their knees
cave in or something like
this um could be a lot of different
things I read a study on Sprint
mechanics a couple months ago that was
very eye openening um where they had the
uh the runners were running on
treadmills and they said you know these
were all Runners who had very poor
running form and they're their knees
caved in when they ran um and they had
too much collapse going on and they they
told the runners I want you when you run
I want you to Envision you know running
in a straight line I don't want your
legs you know caving inwards and I want
you to focus using your glute when you
run I want that glute to contract and
so uh it dramatically improved their
running mechanics and every time I see a
study where they're using neuromuscular
training or re-education or motor
control training it always improves
mechanics every time I've I I I mean
pretty much every study that comes out
it always shows improvements but the
same can't be said for strength training
so I use to think you know okay this
person's knees are collapsing when they
land or when they jump and I would think
okay I just got to give them you know
give them X band walks give them Sumo
walks monster walks things like this
have them put a banner on their knees
and have them Squat and and that's going
to automatically solve the problem well
it doesn't automatically solve the
problem think about it you know why did
they start collapsing in the first place
it's probably because of weak you know
glute medius upper glutes Max um hip
rotators
these muscles were weak and they start
you know so they initially learned how
to jump and land with their knees caving
in but they have practice that and
reinforce that um thousands and possibly
hundreds of thousands a Time on the
field on the court in practices and
scrimmages this is the way they their
brain knows how to jump how to land um
and so you're trying to reprogram that
you're going to get a lot more bang for
your book by using you know
neuromuscular re re-education than using
just strength training because you can
get the muscles stronger and that does
not automatically mean that they're
going to improve their mechanics so to
me uh you get a lot more bang for your
buck when you do something like this
film you know I have a flip Cam that I'm
using right now film them jumping you
know and if you have some sort of
software you can show them in slow
motion that's great I don't have that I
just will replay it I'll plug it into
the computer so I have a nice big screen
and I show them on my computer all right
watch when you jump watch when you squat
watch when you land Watch What Happens
you know your knees cave in see that a
lot of times they don't even know that's
what's happening and they're like oh and
then you say ideally your knees are
supposed to track over your toes you
know when you jump I want you right here
not right here and then you you you have
them practice and then you show them
again all right it's a little bit better
still not perfect then you show them
again oh okay that's how it's supposed
to look and then now they will remember
this every time they jump every time
they're running whatever you're trying
to improve now they're thinking okay I
got to make sure my knees track over my
toes or whatever and then they will
eventually you know this will become
automatic for them so I've seen you know
different studies on on motor control
training and you
know I read something once that it takes
10,000 repetitions to form a motor
engram a motor engram is something like
a you know it's like a an automatic
movement habit a memorized movement
pattern and I don't think there's some
definite number whether it's 10,000 or
1,000 or 100,000 it probably depends on
the person but they're going to get
there a lot quicker they're going to
improve their form a lot quicker when
you use neuromuscular retraining
compared to strength training now that
doesn't mean you shouldn't do xand walks
and monster walks and things like that
glute activation work has been shown to
improve subsequent power production a
lot lot of coaches use you know glute
activation training in their in their
Dynamic warmup and and it's a good thing
to do and I think I personally believe
that the best strategy to improve
someone's form okay if they are landing
in valgus collapse strengthen their
muscles um do the glute activation and
the warmup but then do a specific
neuromuscular re-education component for
those people and they're going to get
their so much faster than they did
before so to summarize what I'm trying
to say is don't just assume that
strength training is the answer I'm
going to give them X band walks you know
and they're going all of a sudden since
they're activating these muscles now
when they jump and they land they're
going to activate those muscles properly
because they've got to coordinate that
into a new skill it's a new skill the
streng most people have the strength
when you look at the the the the EMG of
jumping and landing and things you know
the glute medus isn't firing at Max
Capacity it's just that you know they is
they've learned to land this way it's a
they've learned to kind of instead of
stabilizing the muscles let their knees
C in stabilize with some of the
ligaments and things like that it's just
um it was probably they originally did
it to make up for weak muscles and now
they've memorized that pattern you've
got to retrain their nervous system to
move in a different fashion and with
enough practice you know perfect
practice makes perfect they will get it
it will become habitual it'll become you
know they will reach
automaticity but you'll get much more
bang for your bug focusing on motor
control training rather than just
strength training but do them both do
the glute activation stuff in the warm
up and then use a separate component of
motor control training and that's going
to give you the most bang for your buck
but this is a topic that you know you
see studies coming out five studies a
month and I'll always look over them and
you know it's strength training doesn't
always work um but but neural
reeducation does work and do them both
do them both but know that one is more
important than the other thanks for
watching